Good morning, everyone having fun at the conference so far?
So as Rob said, I have been doing things with 30 and 40-year-old computers for the fun of it
So it brings us to today's plenary
We are going to make a simple Commodore 64 game in C++ 17 today
All right, before we get started
Who all here regularly needs to program for desktop and server systems arm, you know
I'm assuming most people prop that yeah, okay, there we go
Powerpoint just crashed
That's very strange
All right
Yeah, it actually seems my computer just rebooted on me so just a moment
So I'm going to actually fully reboot my computer now and
Without the HDMI cable plugged in and we'll continue the poll so the first question was who all has to program for regular computers
That's every one basically right who programs for microcontrollers
So that's a I don't know 10% of people so
Does anyone here regularly have to program for 40-year-old 8-bit CPUs by any chance?
8 8-bit CPUs but not really what are you programming for if you are does if you are not do 16-bit math
16-bit emulated okay, so um today
While we wait for my computer to reboot we are
Um, we're gonna make this game in for the counter 64 and we're gonna do it in C++ 17 and we're gonna have fun while doing it
So the point is what we're doing here today is not going to be a hundred percent
Applicable because rarely do people have to program on 40-year-old computers
but
It's still gonna be fun and it'll be something that hopefully you can take away from it that you can apply to your normal daily jobs
My computer is almost done rebooting and
So
We did that
Going to implement a simple game in C++ 17. We're gonna have fun. Oh, I'm not gonna program every single line live
People tell me on my YouTube videos that when I don't speed up all the programming stuff
It gets really boring, so we're not gonna do every line live
So we're gonna be using matgodbolts compiler explorer is everyone familiar with gcc.godbolt.org
Yeah
So if you're not already following mat on twitter follow him right now
He has like 989 followers when I look to this morning. Let's just like
Get him over a thousand and so we can go hey the presentation must be going right now
We're going to be using a
latest version of
Cling from get so that we get all the C++ 17 features that we want
And we're gonna be using an x86 to 6502 conversion tool
We're not actually compiling directly for the 6502 processor and I'll fill in the details on that
So I I personally grew up using the Commodore 64
It was the second computer that my family had and I didn't really understand what it was doing
I just programmed in basic and
You did some peaks and pokes and stuff, but never really understood the architecture
I had decided today
I wanted to learn more about the Commodore, but why not use my favorite programming language while doing it
Of course no modern compilers officially support the 40-year-old CPU in this Commodore
So we're going to use our modern C++ compiler with full optimizations enabled because we want to generate the most simple code possible
And we're also going to be asking the compiler to output
32-bit 386 instructions again to keep it as simple as possible
And then we're going to translate this to 6502 code for the Commodore 64
Most people consider this to be absolutely insane
I actually have a comment on my YouTube video that says this is the stupidest thing I've ever seen
Which seems like a pretty low bar to me
But
Uh, it turns out this is actually a little bit easier than um
Riding a 65-bit 2 backend for LLVM
There's several people before me tried to do it who know more about these things than I do
And they were not successful so I didn't bother trying
And also sometimes doing the crazy thing is more fun
Summing it's not when you're at work
So this is what our translation looks like
If you know some assembly language
Cool you can probably follow this the first line is saying we're moving the value 10 into the register called AL
And then on this the right side is a 65-bit 2 version
You cannot directly load values into memory on the um
On the 65-bit 2 so we're saying load the accumulator with the value 10
Then store that into memory location three
I've done some mapping between next 86 registers and zero page on the Commodore
Um, but if you can read this cool if you can't
Rule of thumb less assembly is better than more
This is the Commodore 64 and you know um
If you don't if you'll just indulge me for just a moment
I am going to start up my VM that I realized was lost when I crashed
So get that booting all right
This is the Commodore 64
It was released in 1982 for $595 which is about $1,500 in today's
Uh
Economy
Has a 1MHz 6510 CPU so that's for the people who are going to correct me
It is technically a 6510 not the 6502
6510 adds an extra IO port that the 6502 does not have
But the technology is from 1975 so it's 41 years old now
It is uh has 64k of RAM and it's an 8-bit CPU with a 16-bit address space
Now comparing this to this computer that I saw on a target ad a couple months ago
It's the latest version of the acer aspire one netbook for $150.0.10 the price
It's at least 5,000 times faster
And that's not taking into account the much higher efficiency of the CPU
And and personally I love the way this worked out
It turns out that two gigs of RAM is exactly 32,768 times more than 64k of RAM
And has 64-bit CPU
So if you know anything about CPU caches what we're going to be creating today can easily fit in the level level one cache of the CPU
Uh maybe a little bit more realistic comparison
Is this ti msp 430 microcontroller it's $5 it's like a buck if you buy it and bulk
Runs at 16 megahertz
66k of RAM 16-bit CPU really on par with what the Commodore has for its processing
And I mentioned this one because it has some level of official gcc and clang support
But I don't really know how good that support is does anyone know
Anyone
Someone said something
Yeah, well
Um
All right, so I'm going to hop back over to my VM during this break
And to make sure I can get it set up
This is where I'll be demonstrating my
Uh compiler explorer
Because I needed a custom build of it
And
All right, that should be good
Okay
Oh
Well, all right, so this is our game we're going to be writing pong it has
The ball that everyone knows it's bouncing around the playing field you've got bouncy walls on the top of the bottom
You've got your score um in the middle and you've got paddles on either side
So this is my 32nd computer architecture intro
For people who aren't familiar
This is what your computer looks like
You have a CPU
Registers can be can operate at the same speed as the processor can they're the fastest way that you can work on anything
They're used for scratch space
The CPU really can't do anything on its own
So it has pins with which it talks to the rest of the world and I know this is an oversimplification
But over its bus it talks to things like RAM and other hardware peripherals
So in the case of say a PC and if we want to go back to the classic PC and the fun
architectures fundamentally unchanged your VGA card or
CGA card would have been plugged in on the bus and it would have been accessed as if
Uh, it were memory on the bus and in the case of the counter 64 this is the VIC2
um graphics processor
And the awesome thing about the Commodore is that you can actually
Look at the motherboard and you can see while there's the CPU and there's all the electrical traces
That run to the RAM and the VIC2 and it's all um
Uh, I mean you can literally trace it out if you want to and see that the RAM and the video processor are attached to the same exact bus that the CPU is attached to
So for the duration of this talk we're going to be playing an overhead game
I am going to put some code up or propose an idea and ask you if we can do this if it will take some overhead at runtime or no overhead at runtime
Just binary and someone suggested to me that I actually have you guys switch sides of the room live
But I don't think that'll work
So with memory mapped devices as I already alluded to their devices that are connected directly to CPU's address bus
And you read and write a specific memory locations to actually control these devices
So in the case of the Commodore 64 that's VIC2 if you write to location d020 the value one. This is
equivalent to 53 to 80 in decimal and you're telling the video controller you want to set the border color to white
and
Let's see
If everything is working
Okay, so this is the latest beta version of the compiler explorer. It's not yet live
But Matt helped me out a lot to get this going
What we have on the left is our C++ code and the middle is the x86 assembly output and on the right is the 6502 assembly output
And I think I'm breaking one of the main rules of giving a plenary session
I'm having a bunch of assembly on the screen, but I'm going with it anyhow
So you can see like line for line here what it's doing. We're simply setting with a reinterpret cast the the
memory location 5 3 2 8 0 to 1
And then the x86 side we're moving the value one into memory location 5 3 2 8 0 this line is
Resetting the eax register to 0 because that's where the return value is stored and then it's returning from main
Since the default return value for main is 0
And then over here the common reversions the same we're loading the value one into the accumulator
Then we're storing the accumulator to 5 3 2 8 0
Then we're zeroing out what I have configured to be the virtual e8 e ax register and we're returning
From main. Okay, so obviously if we're doing lots of memory access
Um with these memory map devices and we're having to um
Uh to do a lot of these reinterpret cast this would start to get ugly
So I'm gonna move this into a function and so the first question is can I move this into a function with some overhead
Let's say some overhead first
I get a handful of hands
Well, can I do it with no overhead?
That's most of everyone
And if again if you have not used the compiler explorer
This is an amazing tool
For being able to see the code compile live
So we're calling a memory 5 3 2 8 0 we're sitting that equal to 1 now this appears as though we have added some overhead
but what we have at the top is
The the function memory itself which is ending up in the final binary and
We also have on the 6502 site. Oh, you've done some stuff that our 6502 translator doesn't understand yet
But really we don't need this to end up in the final binary
Because it has been in line for us
So we're gonna put it in an anonymous namespace which is essentially making the function static
And then the compiler helpfully doesn't put it in the resulting binary for us. So we get a cleaner view of what we're doing
And this code has a problem does anyone have any idea what it is actually be great. You can yell answers at me. I'll repeat them
You need volatile who said that
Uh
Way in the back all the cool kids
all right
So
If we wanted to set the background color first to actually let's do this to white
Then we want to set it to black compiler out smarts us it says um you set that memory location then didn't read from it
Then you set it again, so I'm gonna throw away the first one and that is not what we want at all
So if we add volatile then we get what we want and we set the two values
So uh now the next thing that I'd like to
um toy with is putting this in a lambda function
So that I have a little helpful wrapper. So it's a little bit more verbose
Um for what I'm doing will that take some overhead
I get one vote for some overhead no overhead is
Everyone else
So
It's kind of impossible to make a mistake when you're using the uh
Live programming here to tell you everything you did wrong along the way
so
border
Of two
So that gets compiled away um perfectly in line. We've got no overhead
But ultimately for the sake of this demo what we want to do is build up um
An object that helps us work with our vick and uh, I guess I should have pulled before who thinks I can do this with no overhead
Uh, so the adding the object doesn't doesn't add anything to it at all the compiler sees that this object has no member data
It's trivially constructible trivially destructible. It's not doing anything
But it's a handy place for us to access our vick registers
So there you have that and also uh, we're using some constexpr and some constants and stuff and it all just goes away. It's great
For some reason my normal windows keyboard shortcuts haven't been working since the reboot
So this leads to video memory and we've discussed the border color five three two eight zero
We've got the background color which is five three two eight one
And then we have the body of the video memory and this is configurable
but by default it is at location 1024
so um
This is just a flat
linear
array of address
space to
Write data to the screen. So if we wanted to write to the fifth column on the third row
We would write to location 85
plus 1024
So we're going to need this capability for displaying um
uh, the scores on the screen
So
Building from our last example and now I don't have the 6502 output displayed anymore
But if anyone has any questions or any concerns about the 6502 is I do have it set up
so that I can switch back and forth between them as soon as it starts
Compiling well it will stick on the x86 from most of this because that's most realistic to what we're doing
The what you guys are going to be doing in your normal jobs
So
Again, we're doing
Plus 10 which is the columns or saying column 10
Plus 11 times 40. It's a 40 column display. So we're writing to the 11th row 10th column the value a
Now this is something that I want to move into our VIC2 object with some overhead
I'm not getting any hands
no overhead
all right
So the compiler can do some really cool stuff
With a constant folding and other things that I don't fully understand
If you went to goers talk by the way yesterday and he broke down how the compiler optimizes away um
uh
Coordinates as really cool you should watch it uh if you didn't go to the top
Oh
Right
I actually need a VIC2 object to work with
So as you can see as you're all have guessed by now
No overhead
compilers able to um
To do all that at compile time and I'd say uh the first time I saw this personally it was moderately surprising to me
I didn't know that it would do that necessarily a function parameters
I mean obviously in the first part yes why wouldn't the compiler multiply this out for you
But I think that's cool
And I really wish I knew why my keyboard shortcuts weren't working
Oh
So uh it's a game we're going to need some colors
Uh the VIC2 on the Commodore 64 supports 16 colors these are approximately the colors that it supports
There's a fair bit of discussion analysis you can find on the internet about what exactly are the colors that the Commodore can display
It's um
So
We have value two is known as red it is anywhere
Not not nearly a pure red it's approximately 136.570
Then we have light red which is 184 or 10598 and these things all have
uh names there's medium gray and light gray and dark gray and purple and light blue and dark blue and
Um, but it differed between Pell and ntsc
And apparently there's a huge variation in the resistors that were used in the color generation hardware of the Commodore
So really every single Commodore produced slightly different colors
But what we want for our purposes
is
Is um to make working with a fixed pellet easier
Uh, I don't want to have to memorize or create some table that tells me that two is red or something
So my idea is that I want to convert from RGB to the nearest available color on the Commodore 64's pellet
And I'm going to do this by pretending that RGB values represent xy coordinates in 3d space
And I'm going to look for that point in space which is closest to our reference RGB that we are looking for
I want to point out
This is not accurate to how the human ic's colors that is a much more complicated process
But we're also only talking about mapping to 16 different colors. So I think it's going to be good
I
Think I know what's happened. I think yes my virtual
Virtual machine here actually opened on the wrong virtual desktop on windows, which is why my keyboard shortcuts aren't working
Oh, well
so
Who thinks that I can do this
Conversion to RGB values a from RGB values to
To the Commodore's pellet with some overhead
Oh, I'm getting some hands back up again who thinks I can do it with no overhead
The majority
So I have this um this code here now. I've created a struct called color
At this num is the index in the Commodore's pellet and we have RGB values
And scrolling down to the bottom. I have created an array of these colors
Zero through 15 and there are approximately RGB values
And the ultimate goal that we want is to be able to do something like border
Equals and I am using some templates for this
Vick dot
So we want to say get red which we saw in our example is um
The value to
Colors
Okay, so I haven't actually implemented nearest color yet
But what I have is a color comparison routine that
Does our um it looks for the distance
It sees which of the two colors is closest to the reference color
So it's just a less than sorting of the colors relative to the reference color that we want then we have our nearest color function
And what we want to do
Is use the min element standard algorithm
Over the set of colors
And
We need to use our color comparison function
I need to put a namespace on
Okay, now the problem we have remaining is that it's returning a color struct
So I need to actually get the index number out
And there we have the resulting code
Which looks a little bit more than
Some overhead
Everyone agrees I think
It's only
Well, I don't know
350 instructions plus a table of data
So anyone have any ideas for how we might be able to get this to use less overhead
Did I hear constexpr
Can anyone think of a simpler way to get this to have less overhead
What's that
Pre-computed table yeah, that could work, but constexpr would kind of get us there I think anyhow
So
Is there some best practice about using const anywhere possible
So anyone ever heard that
So what happens if we make our static or ray here of color data
Const
So if you don't currently use const anywhere you can I bet you will after this talk
This brings us to our daily programming puzzle. I wanted to go ahead and introduce it during my talk
We're not using constexpr which is what everyone in the audience said that I should be doing
What we did with const here works because the compiler happened to be able to optimize it and it's interesting
I'm using clang with
Gcc's standard library here. I'm not using a libc++
And that was the only combination I found where the compiler and standard library were actually able to fully optimize that away
With adding const to it, but you can do with const expression
And I have solved it otherwise I wouldn't be giving it up here as a programming puzzle for you guys
So the puzzle is to make the nearest color function fully constexpr enabled and in your programming puzzle
You're going to have some static asserts that prove that you made it constexpr enabled
And if you exceed there's a following puzzle excuse me to sort the pellet by luma at compile time
And then figure out what are the lightest and darkest colors in the pellet
Oh, and you have to use c++14
It's actually almost trivial to do this in c++17 because of the extra constexpr support that we're getting in c++17 for standard array
But you don't have that you guys you lost us 14
So we're going to help you appreciate everything that you're going to be gaining with c++17
So what is a game without input need a joystick
Commodore 64 has two joystick ports
And of course the joysticks are accessed via the memory map like everything else on the Commodore 64 since the
6502 only has its address bus
Talk out of
Hopefully the designers at Commodore
Made memory port b be joystick one and memory port a be joystick number two
Which
Anyone else grew up using the commodore 64
Wow a lot of people did you ever notice that almost every game used port two for player for the player if it was a single player game
You ever wonder why i think this is why because it was
It was the first space in memory to access. I don't know maybe not there's also some interesting interaction between the joystick port and the keyboard um scan
So the uh the logics inverted on our joystick data
So if bit zero is not set then we know that up has been pressed if bit one is not set we know is down as pressed etc
To fire it works the same for both joysticks
So i have here
Um added to our example we've still got our victus struct
We've added a couple of things we have a test bit function. This just simply returns true with a bit of set
It's pretty straightforward. I've actually marked that constexpr
And we have a joystick
And in our joystick um
We kind of have to do this inversion logic. So if the port number the um i'm doing it based off of the ports
How they're actually labeled on the Commodore
So if you're asking for port number two then i'm giving you port letter a and if you ask for not port number two
I give you port letter b
And i'm using actually a delegating constructor here which uh i thought was kind of a neat way to handle it personally
So on my first constructor it takes a port data all port data is as a you went eight
And in the second constructor i'm asking for a port number it converts uh calls the del uh calls the other constructor
And i set the up down left right fire
So this is what we have is uh and i'm using c++17s if initializer list here if you haven't seen the syntax yet
So the first line is uh an initialization and the second uh a second
Expression is what we're actually testing against
So i'm asking for joystick
port number one and if the fire button is pressed then i want to set the background color equal to one
And as you can see the compiler has completely um
It's completely done away with everything that i typed on essentially
Where it's simply saying is the fifth bit of the memory location five three six two one set
If it is
Then we want to jump up here move the value one and two
memory location five three two eight one and if not then we jump um into the loop and test again
So it's handled all of the delegating constructor
It's completely eliminated our entire data structure even though it actually does contain data now
Actually, it's eliminated two data structures for us because our temporary port data and our
uh bowls that are in here and the compiler continues to outsmart us along the way
If we wanted to say if up and fire are pressed at the same time
Now it has merged those into one operation and it's saying our bits
five and bit
zero set
Then it continues on
And you can continue
to add things to it
And it doesn't get much more complicated in that and as as everyone seen the if initializer lists anyone
Few some half okay, so uh
May as well go into that just a second with the if initializer list the value that is initialized in the if statement is available in the else block also
So I could say else
If
Down is pressed and the compiler continues to
Compile all this away. So we're using our nith initializer list or objects without any overhead
So everyone familiar with rai i i would hope so
Okay
Resource acquisition is initialization
Uh, essentially we're using constructors and destructors to manage the state and resources of our program
A lot of people consider this to be the greatest strength of c++
But I would like you to consider thinking about it differently
Well-defined object lifetime as c++ is greatest strength
C++ is not the only language with constructors and destructors, but it is one of very few languages where you know exactly when those things are going to be called
So who thinks that we can put some rai ii to use with some overhead
So
Two and with no overhead
Okay, let's see what we got
So what what I want to do is
Uh, so a little bit of a little bit of background for sorry
This code if you haven't noticed is is really really tight. We're talking two instructions
essentially right a couple of jumps so it can operate
Many times faster than
Then then the screen is updating so what we can actually see in this code is the background color
Changing several times per raster line as the computer is drawing the rows on the screen and you would end up with one color that's taking up
You know like ten pixels and then another ten another ten another ten
So what we need to do is put some sort of
Garden here to prevent us from updating but once a frame and I'm going to do that
By checking to see if we are on the 240th raster line and if we are we know we're outside of the normal background drawing area
So
So a simple busy loop we wait until we get to the 240th line once we have we continue on and we're willing to update the background color and
And that is here negative 16 is to his complement 8 bit math for 240
Now we just for the fun of it want to increment the border color
On every loop
Is that on every loop iteration whether or not the joystick fire button is being pressed
So this seems to me
Like a logical place to use our AI we want something that will guard us and block us until we have actually
Reach the 240th raster line and then we want to do something on destruction on the border
So I'm going to create a new function called frame on my victu
object
And in here I'm going to create an inner struct
That has our constructor and a destructor
And
It needs to keep a reference to its parent victu object because to operate on the border it needs to have the victu object to do that
Compilers now complaining at us because we have an uninitialized reference in our object no big deal
And then we'll use our initializer list
and
Then we return a frame object
That takes a reference to the parent object
And now we're going to move into our constructor
And destructor
So
So to make this work
And we get the exact same code that we started with
So we are effectively using our AI with some move operations
There's no copies of our frame object being created. It just does what we want it to do
That's
I don't know if I'm relying on a
Not yet guaranteed by the standard optimization for return value optimization
Just anyone answer that
But I can by enabling move constructors
so
Just for clarity by putting this destructor in here the compiler is not creating for us our move operations by putting in your own destructor
You've disabled them implicitly
So if I wanted to be fully correct follow the rule of zero here, which I highly recommend
Then we would need to do some
Move constructor defaults and stuff to make sure they're not default they're not disabled but anyhow
So this is what we wanted so at this point I said to myself hey maybe I've gone off the reservation
I need to make sure that this actually still doesn't have any overhead compared to writing all of this code by hand and
Do we want to take any guesses as to whether or not this will look the same
Let's see do we at this point have no overhead still
Hmm most people say we still have no overhead
So I have my r a i i sanity check where it is just a bunch of reinterpret casts and calls to memory locations
For the joystick port and the incrementing of the background and border color
So
This looks different
And does anyone know why
Yes, we still have a volatile problem and it's interesting that it was like two weeks into preparing this talk that I realized technically
I was doing my reinterpret casts wrong this entire time the compiler
checks the memory location five three two six six exactly once
And if it is not equal to 240 it
jumps down to this infinite busy loop
So we need to add volatile
Here we can add it and now we have proven to ourselves
We still have no overhead
Oh
There we go
Game needs sprites everyone familiar with the sprite is
Little movable object on the screen basically let's call it that
Conor 64 or the victu supports eight hardware sprites these hardware sprites have hardware sprite collision detection
Which is a pixel level I believe which is pretty cool
So if two things hit each other then you get the hard work and notify you that you've had a collision
And the sprites are 24 by 21 pixels each so
I'm going to point out that technically it has eight hardware sprites per scan line people will do lots of tricks of updating the sprites as the display is being drawn
Because as I already pointed out we can actually do things in the middle of the frame easily
So if you ever play a game on an old computer and it has more than whatever technically says it can support for sprites
It's because they're updating the locations during the middle of the screen draw
Sprites can be single color or multi color and they can have their height or width doubled
And that's something we'll be taking advantage of but I'm not going to go into a lot of details
Monochrome sprites each bit represents one pixel we have a smiley face
If we take a stripe out of the middle of where the eyes are
And assign bit patterns to this is this is literally a bit map
And convert that to decimal we have the values that we need to write to memory to create our sprite for the Commodore 64
So if we do this for the entire thing this is what we end up with
This is the array of data on the right that we need to write in now what I wanted to do
Is have the Commodore or excuse me have the compiler actually compile my sprite data for me
So I've written this
This is our bouncy ball
um
It is the bitmap in the source code
And I am passing this to our make sprite function the make sprite function is a variadic template
That is writing all of the pixel data to this specific location we wanted to go to
And then this is our right pixel implementation that I need to actually right now
So at memory location
Locke we want to assign the value
And you guys get to watch me type for a minute
Every time I practice the test I get confused at d4 equals d4 shifted left four times because I can't remember which number is going up and which number is going down
Okay
We are writing the very first byte of our sprite data to the specific memory location we wanted to go to which is 12288
And that's a detail of the default configuration of where the sprite data stored on the Commodore not worth going into but we're sticking with the defaults for the stuff
Now we need to actually write the rest of the sprite data and to do that we're going to call right pixel
recursively for the next
Memory location and the rest of the sprite data
big compiler
Anyone know why
Well I'm missing the 0th case
So once we run out of data
As expecting to call a function that has no
Ah there we go
So this takes
A second to compile
There we have it
We have had the compiler compile for us our
sprite
resources
And it is writing into memory all the specific data we want and I know there are many different ways to do this
In fact, it would be possible to have it create a table and then do a loop that moves the data into the
appropriate memory space but that's not what I wanted to do for this example
So we're actually asking the compiler to do a lot of work
And is anyone
Sorry about the switching back and forth
Should be able to get that
Anyone aware of how many functions parameters and how many function calls we just made
So you want to throw any guesses out
It's a big room to do this with but I'm going to do it anyhow
I'll give you a hint
Remember that that was 24 by 21 pixels
What's that
To 20 no more than that
504 plus one because you're forgetting the memory location
504 parameters being passed to the first function and how many recursive function calls are we making
Plus one because of the zero case
So we just asked the compiler at compile time to optimize away
64 deep recursive function call with 505 parameters to it
Well, I think we should give a hand to the compiler developers
So multi-color sprites what's the world fun without some color
Now we have a color version of our smiley face if you notice the pixels are double wide now what we have is
Each two bits
Represents one color and represents two pixels. So essentially you have each pixel is double wide
Does that make sense if we keep moving forward these are the color values
For each of these and then if we split that into binary we have our
Three octets like we did with the monochrome
That gives us the values that we want
And we do the same process again
So this is our final data
See if I can start getting smarter about switching back and forth
So I've already stubborn all of our
Multi-color sprite stuff
This is the paddle that we'll be using it is long and skinny because the pixels are double wide so when this is
You know expanded out by the computer. It's going to be square
But then I'm using the hardware capabilities of
doubling the height of it
So that actually gives me square pixels because the pixels were already scaled vertically
Now I'm going or horizontally and now I'm going to scale them vertically
But we'll see that in the demo
So we are not compiling at the moment
Because we have a minor problem the
Multi-color pixels have less data than the monochrome pixels
So we need some way to choose between these two things at compile time
And we could do this with lots of fun like spin A things or we could do it by simply having
a different function call from the beginning
So instead of make sprite I had make color sprite
But instead I decided to take advantage of c++17's if constexpr
so I can do a
compile time switch with if constexpr
And the compiler chooses the correct version at compile time the version that doesn't need to get called to just goes way
Everything works great
So now we have full support for color or monochrome sprite data being compiled at compile time by the compiler
Okay, time to
Sorry bring this together
But a quick note
The Commodore 64 screen is 200 pixels tall and 320 pixels wide
The Commodore is an 8-bit CPU
So it can only go to 255
Now obviously the Commodore hardware has ways of dealing with this
But for the sake of this demo I wanted to stick to 8-bit math
So the playing field
I've limited it to 255 pixels wide
So this is our final game now we have our memory functions our
Color data test bit
We have our joystick stuff that we've been talking about and
A key part of the joystick that I
kept forgetting to mention when we were actually talking about the joystick
But I've created this function called direction vector and it returns
An xy pair for what
What direction the joystick is being pressed in so the first values negative one if it's left one if it's right up and down
So we're using a standard pair for that
And then I've created a couple handy functions for myself. They'll let me do
pairwise addition and pairwise multiplication of our pairs
And I've added a new function called setbit
This is necessary for things like setting up the registers for the sprite data
We have our player object it
Has an update position member where it is using the direction vector data from the joystick to move the
Paddle up or down moving it three pixels at a time
We've got
Hello, we've got a
The
Score it keeps track of its own score which we are storing for the sake of this in an ASCII so I can just write the actual character code to the screen
And we've got a pair of volatile
UN8 references that are the position of the current players paddle on the screen
Our VIC2 object is now fully fleshed out
With our border background display color comparison nearest color our frame object that we're just discussing
But now the frame actually
It has references to the two players
And it uses those references to get the score data displays that
And our
Sprite data
Then our enabled sprite now has been fully fleshed out and we have
This new function called sprite collisions and I am going to
I am returning a tuple of
all of the
Collision bits so if there's been a collision involving sprite zero then the first bit is set
et cetera
Sprite colors
Okay, so this brings us so at the moment
I have the sprite data and all the boilerplate stuff commented out because I don't want it to get in the way of
Are looking at the assembly
So this is what our game logic becomes we have the ball velocity
Which starts out as being x
1 y1 so it's moving in the up right direction
We have a lambda reset ball. This is called every time someone scores. We need to reset the ball back to the middle of the screen
We have our players when where they are set
What sprites they are using and where the paddle is on the screen
And here we are using c++ 17 destructuring capability to
Get out all of the sprite collision data from our sprite collision function
And we're just testing to see was sprite zero
Which is the ball and involved in a collision with sprite one or sprite two which are the two paddles
If it was then we want to invert the velocity x velocity of the ball
So if it was moving left now it's moving right
If it was moving right now it's moving left
And then we need to bounce the ball out of the collision area otherwise it has the tendency to get stuck inside the paddle and do this thing
It's
not what you want
And so we can see over here all of this the the sprite collision logic we had a tuple in there and we had
We have our destructuring and then we do our comparisons here the compiler is
doing lots of
smart things and simplifying this into a pretty simple read from the sprite collision data
And then a couple of comparisons to figure out where the interactions were
Then we update the paddle positions based on
What the user is pressing on the joystick
And now here. This is this is the end of it. We've got our
Ball x and ball way a ball y
Uh, that's current location. So if the ball has gone up to the top of the screen which is row 45
Then we need to bounce it back down or if it's gone to the bottom we need to bounce it back up
So we are using those overloads for times equals on sd pair that I
showed a minute ago to again invert the y velocity of the ball and this
Logic
Gets compiled down to very little also actually that
Well
And if the ball has gone all the way to the left side of the screen then player one is square player two is scored because it's gone off the left side of the playing field
If it's gone all the to the right side of the screen then player one is scored and we update the score
So the entire game compiles not including the boilerplate to 83 instructions
So I don't know
Really what this equivalent would be equivalent on a PC if you could do this, but I'm guessing somewhere in the
billion frames per second ballpark
maybe
I like except for the fact that we're intentionally limiting it to one update per per frame which we have to do on the
Commodore by the way the game is completely unplayable if we don't limit it to one update per frame
So if we
Uncomment our boilerplate
We will now see all of the sprite data being compiled for us at the top of the output
And then the rest of the program logic it's compiling two sprite resources this time so that's
One and a half times the amount of work that we were talking about before
But you can see straight forward sprite one sprite two oh I didn't mention this explicitly, but the
The two paddles are sharing the same sprite data
But the Commodore can have different colors configured for the paddles so we are giving them different colors
So
The entire game is 231 instructions on x86 and on the 6502 it's a little bit bigger
It's
That's
Because I am doing an imperfect translation it's somewhere in the 400 and
Instructions 420
There we go 419 instructions and
What this means is the entire game including sprite resources compiles to 1,000 five bytes
basically
So does anyone want to actually see the game played by the way
All right
We're going to attempt to do that with
My Commodore 64 that I brought to the presentation
Now unfortunately we did have some technical difficulties while setting up and it would seem that
I may have sustained a little bit of hardware damage and transit so we'll see what can happen
I am going to need a volunteer on stage. I know I talked to her but if he's here you can come up
Let's see if we can get this going
It is that is an official original Atari 2600 joystick now
It's I also grew up with them
This is why I actually bought these on ebay just for this because this was the joystick I played all of my Commodore games with
So here's hoping our video is going to work at which point I'm going to need camera on stage
All right minor technical difficulties, but we do have a display up here
So as soon as it gets up there
So you'll be the player on the right I set this up intentionally
Hopefully we can actually see the screen. I've not seen this before. No, you have not this is um
If anyone's curious I actually got it onto the Commodore 64 by using this thing called the SD-2 IEC
Which is a teeny tiny little 1541 disk drive that uses an SD card and it actually
Plugs into the original interface that the Commodore expected
It's amazing that these things like these things are still being developed people love this hardware
The video cable that I'm using hey we're on screen the video cable I'm using is
Today manufactured like it's brand new from a
A manufacturer in the UK who's making us video output for the Commodore 64
Gonna load the directory from the SD card
It's really hard since I can't really actually see the screen
Okay, and what we have is pong.2.cpp.prg
Little verbose, but it works
Now if anyone's curious the assembler in tools that I used actually um
Load the game into my relocation 4096. So I've loaded the game
But to actually get it to run I need to
Jump to that memory location and there we have
Can you see the screen herb
It's a little slow it needs to actually at some point speed up, but there we have that
I
I hope the theme that I went for is not completely lost on the screen here
So that there is no end to this game so whenever we get bored
Yeah, and we still have a little
Ah stuck in the paddle
Oh
Oh, there's actually a little
If anyone didn't notice I didn't put any limits on where the paddle can go so you can get a little bit of a cheater uh
Scroll around there
All right, thank you herb excuse me
I'm glad that worked
All right
All right, why why did what we did work um we used straightforward logic in our code this is um
The simpler code that you can write and see those plus the better the compiler can work with that basically
So we have very little branching and in some cases which I didn't dig into it maybe as much as I could have
We actually had branching that the compiler got rid of
We had branching saying is if if these states are true on the joystick and the compiler said no no no
I don't need to do any branching here
I'm going to take these values and do a couple of bit shifts and I'm going to load them into some other registers and then just
Do the right thing and and it can do that
So we let the compiler work for us. We've got function inlining was huge if you didn't notice
There were no function calls even though we had lots of function calls
So anyone paying enough attention to notice how much ram we actually used if you don't include the sprite data
Yeah, zero bytes of ram it uh the compiler actually
Was able to map every single variable every single thing we did directly to register allocation
And this is on a 386
386 compiler output that I'm asking for which is um
I don't know
I don't remember it has like 16 registers or something
Compared to a current
Intel architecture does anyone know how many registers a current intel has
Anyone
I I don't actually I haven't managed to count that hot yet
It's in the like hundreds or something and it doesn't even matter because if you're writing to registers
And you can talk to hardware people that know more about this than I do
The CPU is going to assign those to virtual registers internally and rearrange everything for you anyhow
So if you keep everything simple
You pretty much don't need to access ram in some cases
And we've heard some mention of the conference already the principle of zero head abstractions zero overhead extract
abstractions and c++
So today we used objects with
How much overhead
Methods zero
Delegating constructors and destructors zero
Lambdas with and without captures
Zero overhead structured bindings from c++ 17 with no overhead
Function calls no overhead c++ new 17 if and it expressions with
Zero overhead and
variatic recursive templates
With zero runtime overhead and even standard algorithms with zero runtime overhead
So
So that brings me to the conclusion as Rob mentioned we host cbvcast check it out and my c++ weekly youtube channel
Which is how I ended up on this stage
um
URL and I've done a couple of videos with a Riley if you want to check them out
So if there's questions
Ask questions
We've already got one. Yeah, hi
Even though it's not in the standard I've noticed that compiler sometimes can deduce concept or if from const
I was just wondering if that's what happens here array. I'm sorry if what happened to it
Sometimes compiler's can deduce const expert from const when you write just const
Can the compiler just deduce const expert from const? I would say
No, I don't believe that's technically what happened. I've seen that happen before. Yes
Uh, and and there's there are rules that say you know in certain cases
The constructors are implicitly const expert
I in some cases I forget the details
But I think it's um just a really a compiler being really smart there because that version of standard array from the standard library
I was using does not have any const expert or that's very few const expert methods on it
Uh, yes. Oh, hey Jason. Great talk. Thanks
Um, you have the recursive template
Formulation are you familiar with um the for each and args
Variety pack expansion style that Vittorio's talk
Yeah, you covered. I did you try that one? No, I didn't try it. I've seen some of that stuff
I was aiming for something that I knew I could easily that the result would easily translate into what I wanted on the 6502
um
But I also wanted to do it all without having to include any boilerplate code
Which I believe I would have to in that case
The for each one. Well, I mean my my curiosity is just with it up my's away. Oh, I don't know
If frequently compiles faster, I think then hold up recursive stuff. Oh, there's Vittorio
Okay, so he said the for each args
Uh after optimization level one on clang and two on gcc goes away
other way around
So yes, it can also go away with probably faster compile time
Awesome talk. Thank you. I was wondering if you compiled this without exception support
If you handle that any I didn't need the bother to try
So did the it just I mean, I'm not using any exceptions
I'm not calling any functions that could throw exceptions. There was no exception code generated. It didn't matter
awesome
Hi, thank you for showing the assembly on the screen. It was very entertaining. Um, I had the question
You know the tricks that you showed they work one time when you're just doing things like that
But in real production code you want to make sure that these things continue to be to be optimized away
As the code gets improved. Do you have any tricks to do static asserts or code size or anything like that to make sure that the
Zero overhead abstractions continue to be zero overhead. I think probably the most important thing is
In my experience, and I'm sure we would get a huge range of answers from the audience
Uh is avoiding dynamic allocations
By doing as much stuff as you can on the stack as pal as possible the compiler is able to do some really amazing things with what it's able to to do from the code
Um, and then I I would suggest actually taking advantage of constexpr
Um as much as possible
Uh, and then and then letting the compiler do its job
Uh, that's uh, okay another question just last one uh
Please in non generic code. Can we get rid of standard pair and use us abstract with named members C++ 11 14 17
I'll tell was tell says that that has zero overhead of a standard pair. So instead of using first and second and custom
Dangerous overloads on the operators for generic standard pair
With generic standard uh, if I understand your question correctly
I mean you can use destruct destructuring of the pairs and you can get away from some of the nonsense of using first and second and keep the code clean
Yeah, okay
Oh
Yes
The the amount of code that the compiler generated after the optimizations was simply stunning
stunningly small. Yes. So do you have any idea what a
hand-rolled say version of pong that was contemporary with the hardware might have consumed in memory?
You know, I do not know but I am assuming that after this video is released on youtube. I will find out
Yes
Don't worry. It's good. So you said you said that this consumes zero runtime memory
I think it's that's not accurate. I think it's better than that
Better than zero because you are using some runtime memory. You're storing the current color you're storing
That's the sprite at runtime
But what you're doing is you're taking advantage of the memory that the hardware is already using any way
And you're using it directly without adding any overhead of your own
So you are using memory that's already there and using it the most efficient way possible which I think is really cool
That's the interesting point
Thank you
Just a good question. How much work was it actually writing the conversion tool from the x86
To the 6502 kind of assembly compared to actually writing the game
Um
It's probably about three times more work than actually writing the game
But I spent a lot of time tweaking the code to try to get what I thought would be the cleanest representation of the
Of the game main loop
possible, but
The 6502 assembler or reassembler I called a reassembler actually got that name from my cousin
It's it took um, I'd say about it maybe a week's worth of work
But the bulk of that work was done in the
Before the C++ weekly YouTube video that led up to where we are today
And it's it's excuse me. It's up on GitHub. I didn't put a link to it in here
But if you look for a x86 to 6502 you can find it and it's
It's pretty good at this point. I would say so one of the comments on my original video
I said I got a comment that said this is the stupidest thing I've ever seen
Um, and the follow on was you it could never work for non-truvial code and I admit that this is crazy
But it can work for non-truvial code and it was really fun to do
How did you go about developing
This sort of example was it something you wrote all at once? Did you write it in chunks?
I mean the way you kind of walked us through looked very interesting, but is that the way you actually made it?
Have to think about that for a second
I
I knew what my goal was and that it was to put a two-player game on the screen live on the converse 64 and
I initially thought I was gonna have to go with something much more simple than pong even and pongs pretty darn simple
The original pong is as implemented in solid state hardware. There's no programming involved
But it's also all in black and white
Um
So I kind of I kind of proved to myself that I could make the game. I wanted to make for this demo and then I
Took where I had started on the YouTube video and I kind of worked towards the middle to get what I wanted
Oh, and how much time do you think this would take you this took you to make sort of like in terms of development?
Was it a week on and off or several weeks of
Toying around with it till you had what you wanted the entire presentation or just the game the game the game
Probably week and a half
Maybe full-time effort
I've noticed that you sprinkled as you said const all over the place
But I've noticed also a static keyword. Can you talk about static and what was the significance of?
Uh, dance. Oh the static keyword. So
Let's see
And the see if I can get there
That was and
This is the most basic example. Oh, but that doesn't have the the palette actually implemented yet
um
Let's see because uh, you know as as we just said this code was kind of generated and
Stages so it's possible the static is not necessary there
But I think it actually is for the compiler to optimize it oh no actually in that version. It's not static
so um
Yeah, the the compiler did the right thing const was the important part
static started from when I was trying to figure out the best way to organize the code to make it as readable as possible on the screen and I had moved it
Outside of the function
Okay, thanks. Oh
I
All right, yes, that's it. Thank you